<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iniunctions with certaine articles to be enquired of in the visitation of the Reuerend Father in Christ, Iohn, by Gods prouidence, Byshop of Norvvich, aswell to the clargie, as to the Churchwardens and quest men of euery seuerall parish within the dioces of Norvvich, [and] to be put in execution, by al the Archdeacons commissaries [and] other officers exercisinge ecclesiasticall iurisdiction, vnder the sayd Bishop in their synodes, visitation, and courtes. In the yeare of our Lord God. 1569.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1569</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Norwich. Bishop (1560-1575 : Parkhurst)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1569</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113334</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848570</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13673</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13673)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 459:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iniunctions with certaine articles to be enquired of in the visitation of the Reuerend Father in Christ, Iohn, by Gods prouidence, Byshop of Norvvich, aswell to the clargie, as to the Churchwardens and quest men of euery seuerall parish within the dioces of Norvvich, [and] to be put in execution, by al the Archdeacons commissaries [and] other officers exercisinge ecclesiasticall iurisdiction, vnder the sayd Bishop in their synodes, visitation, and courtes. In the yeare of our Lord God. 1569.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1569</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Norwich. Bishop (1560-1575 : Parkhurst)</author>
                  <author>Parkhurst, John, 1512?-1575.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [H. Middleton? for] Iohn VValley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Aprilis 15. [1569]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>The Trinity College (University of Cambridge) Library copy has a cancel slip with "serue" pasted over "ferme" on A2v line 16; not present in the Bodleian Library copy--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Diocese of Norwich --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13673:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13673:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Iniunctions with certaine Articles to be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, in the
Viſitation of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Father in Chriſt, <hi>Iohn,</hi> by Gods
prouidence, Byſhop of <hi>Norvvich,</hi> aſwell to the Clargie, as to the
Churchwardens and queſt men of euery ſeuerall pariſh within the dioces of
<hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvich,</hi> &amp; to be put in execution, by al the Archdeacons
Commiſſaries &amp; other officers exerciſinge eccleſiaſticall
iuriſdiction, under the ſayd Biſhop in their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes, Viſitation, and
Courtes.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>In the yeare of our Lord God. 1569.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by Iohn VValley. Aprilis. 15.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:13673:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13673:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Iniunctions.</hi> ¶ INIVNCTIONS VVITH CER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
Articles to be enquired of, in the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Reuerend father in
Chriſt, Iohn, by gods prouidence, Bishop of Norvvich. &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="clergy" type="articles">
               <head>¶ For the Clargie.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N primis, you muſt endeuour ſo to order
&amp; frame your ſelues in the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of Gods true Religion, due
adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the reuerent and diſtincte ſaying
or ſinging of the Common prayer, as hath bene preſcribed and ſette forthe
vnto you beefore tyme, aſwell by the booke of Common prayer ſet forth to be
vſed through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Realme, as by ſondry Iniunctions ſet foorth for
that purpoſe. And that you take great heede, that your lyues and
conuerſations be ſuch euery way, as no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon haue cauſe to be
offended thereby, ſomuch as in you lieth.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Item, ye ſhall not take vppon you to
Preach, or Expounde the Scriptures by way of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or otherwiſe, in
your owne Church or elſe where, vnleſſe you bee admitted thereto by the
moſte Reuerend Father, the Archbyſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> or the
Biſhop of the Dioces.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Item, you ſhall not marie or ſuffer to be
mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within any of your cures, any perſonne or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb facs="tcp:13673:3"/>that come lately out of any other
Dioces, vnleſſe ſuche perſons bring with them ſufficient
teſtimoniall vnder the Seale of the Ordinarie of the Dioces from whence he or
they ſhal come, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying ſuch perſon or perſons to be free and
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maryed, and at their liberty to mary according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Item, at ſuch tymes as ye ſhall vſe the
peram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation in the <hi>Rogation</hi> dayes for the boundes of your pariſh,
you ſhall not vſe any ſurples vppon you, or ſtay at any croſſe, or
ſuffer any banners, to be caried, or other ſuperſtition to be vſed, but
one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly geue GOD thanks, and vſe ſuch good order of prayers and Homelies, as
be appointed by the Queenes maieſties authoritie in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Item none of you ſhall ferme one cure or
more within this Dioces, without ſpeciall lycence in wryting vnder the
Biſhops Seale.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Finally, ye ſhall diligently obſerue and
put in vre, all ſuch Orders &amp; Iniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as haue ben ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed you
before tyme, aſwell by the Iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the queenes maieſtie, as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburyes</hi> grace, and the Biſhop of the
Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="churchwardens" type="articles">
               <head>¶ For the Churchvvardens, Queſtmen and
others.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Item, that no Parſon Vicar, propriatorie,
or fermer of any benefice, doe admit any Miniſter or
<pb facs="tcp:13673:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Curate to ſerue his ſaid
benefice, vnleſſe ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall firſt ſhow his letters of
Orders, where he was made Myniſter, and haue alſo ſufficient
teſtimoniall vnder the Seale of the Ordinarye, from whence he commeth, with
lycence from the Biſhop to ſerue accordingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Item, that in great Churches where all the
people cannot conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly heare their miniſter, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church wardens &amp;
other, to whome that charge belongeth, ſhal prouide and appoint, a decent and
a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient ſeate in the body of the church, where the ſayd miniſter may
ſit or ſtand, and ſay the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice, that all the congregation
may heare and be edified therewith. And that in ſmaller churches, ther be
ſome conuenient ſeate without the chauncell dore for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Item, that vppon all ſainctes daye and
other like times, ther be no ringing of belles after Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer, or any
other ſuperſtitious ceremony vſed, to the maintenaunce of poperie, or
praying for the dead, &amp; that if any ſuch ſhalbe hence forth vſed, the
ſame with the names of ſuche as ſhall offende therein, to bee preſented
to the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Item, that no perſon or perſons calling
them ſelues lordes of miſrule in the Chriſtmas tyme, or other vnreuerent
perſons at any other tyme, preſume to come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church vnreuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly
play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their lewd partes, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcoffing, ieſting, or rebal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry talke,
&amp; if any ſuch haue alredy offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded herein, <pb facs="tcp:13673:4"/>to
preſent them and their names to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Item, for auoydinge of vnlawfull mariages,
you ſhall prouide in euery of your Churches, a certayne table for the degrees
of Mariage laſt ſet forth by the foreſayde moſt Reuerend Father in God
<hi>Mathevv,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to be ſette vp in
ſome conuenient place of the ſayd Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Finally, you ſhall carefully and diligently
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, that all ſuch good Orders &amp; Iniunctions, as haue ben
preſcribed &amp; appointed beefore time, ſhalbe duly by you put in
execution, ſo far forthe, as they concerne any of you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <p>
                  <hi>¶ Articles to be enquired of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> IN primis, whether your Diuine ſeruice be
ſayde or ſong in due tyme and reuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the Sacraments duely and
reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly myniſtred in ſuch decent apparel, as is appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the laws,
the Queenes maieſties Iniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other orders ſet forthe by publike
auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Item, whether the Queenes maieſties
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctions, be quarterly read in your Churches, &amp; a declaration read
twyſe euery yeare, which was ſet forth by bothe the Archbiſhops and the
reſte of the Byſhops, concerning certayne principall pointes of Religion,
for the vnitie of Doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Item, whether you haue in your Churche a
<pb facs="tcp:13673:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Bible,</hi> of the
largeſt volume, the <hi>Paraphraſis,</hi> of <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> in
Engliſh, with the <hi>Homelies,</hi> &amp; all other boks requiſite, for
the Adminiſtration of Diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. And whether the <hi>Homelies</hi> be
duely and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly read.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Item, whether you haue in your Church a
decent Pulpit and Communion table furniſhed and placed as becommeth, with a
comly commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion cup, with a couer, and a cheſt or poore mans boxe, and the
collection and diſtribution, for the poore, made according to a ſtatute in
that behalfe prouided:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Item, whether any perſon or perſons haue
pulled downe, any Church, Chappell, or Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, almes houſe, or belles, or
any part thereof, or haue felled or ſpoyled any wood or tymber in any Church
yarde, or haue ſolde any church goodes: to whome, what it was, and for what
price.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Item, whether your Church, Chauncel, and your
Parſonage and Vicaredge houſe, be well &amp; ſufficiently repaired and
maintained, &amp; whether that your Church yard be well kept and fenced,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Item, whether your Rodeloftes, Images,
Tabernacles, and all other monuments of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie be pulled downe and defaced,
and youre Church and Chauncell decently reformed. And whether you know of any
Popiſh and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bookes, Images, veſtments, or ſuch lyke,
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining within your pariſh and in whoſe hands they bee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13673:5"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Item, whether your Preachers &amp;
Miniſters doe erneſtly and diligently teache theyr Auditory and
pariſhiners, to lyue in faythfull and humble obedience to almighty GOD, the
Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and all and ſinguler hir officers, aſwell ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
as temporal, exhorting them from all kind of Idolatrie, ſuperſtition, and
other vices.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Item whether your Miniſter be geuen to
fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre, whordome, dronkenneſſe, or other like notorious vices, or
doe haunt or frequent any ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious houſe or company, or any vaine
paſtimes as hawking, hunting, diſing, carding, and ſuche like vanities,
and geue not him ſelfe to prayer, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, almes dedes, with ſuch like.
And whether he pray diligently for the proſperous eſtate of the Queenes
maieſtie, as to duety belongeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Item, whether your Myniſter doe eudeuour
him ſelfe diligently to teach &amp; inſtruct the youth of the pariſh, the
<hi>Catechiſme,</hi> and do otherwiſe ſee them brought vp in the feare of
God, and in due obedience and reuerence, to their parentes, may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and
elders.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Item, whether your curate or Miniſter haue
admitted any to Preache within your pariſhe church not being lawfully
lycenſed thereunto, or haue refuſed any ſuche as are licenſed, and
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you haue your quarter ſermons.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Item, whether you know of any ſectaries,
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe to make any priuate conuenticles in priuate mens houſes, in
contempt of the lawes and good <pb facs="tcp:13673:5"/>orders
ſet forthe by authoritie, and doe preache, teach, or miniſter the
Sacraments there, and by that meanes attempt to withdrawe the people from due
obedience, and to raiſe and maintaine ſciſmes &amp; ſectes, who they
are that ſo doe, where they do it, and what be the articles and contents of
their doctrine and opinions.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> Item, whether there be any Miniſter,
Prieſt, or other perſone or perſons whatſoeuer within your pariſh,
that doeth willingly, ſinbburnely, or negligently, abſent him ſelfe from
the church and receuinge of the Sacramentes, and do refuſe to contribute to
the poore mens box, and that walk vp and downe iangling and talking in the tyme
of Common praier, or adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, any that vſe any
other booke of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers then is ſet forth by publike authoritie, or that haue
not communicated thriſe euery yeare at the leaſt, nor ſubmit him ſelfe
to the laws and orders ſet forth by common authoritie, and where ſuche
perſon or perſons doe remaine, and who they are that doe maintaine
them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Item whether your Vicar or Parſon be
reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and kepeth hoſpitalitie in and vppon hys benefice, &amp; howe
many benefices he hath, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their names.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> Item, who is patroue of your benefice,
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he witholde the glebe landes or tithes pertayning to the ſame,
or any parte thereof, or vſeth any ſimonicall pactes in the beſtowinge of
<pb facs="tcp:13673:6"/>his ſayd benefice, and whether he
or any in hys name, hath in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of the vacation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, taken the
fruits and profits thereof, and by what authoritie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Item, whether ye know any Parſon or Vicar,
that ſel their benefice to meare lay men, abſenting them ſelues from the
ſame, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defacing of their callinge, decay of hoſpitalitie, contempt of
the lawes, neglecting of their duties, bothe towards God, and the Queenes
maieſtie, and euill exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the church of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> Item, whether your church be vacant, &amp;
how long it hath ben ſo, and what is the cauſe therof.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> Item, whether you know, any maintainers of
foren power, letters or hinderers of Gods holy word, and ſlaunderers of the
Preachers or of the miniſtery or publike prayer, or that defend or hold any
opinions againſte them or any of them, who they are expreſſing their
names, and what was theyr communication.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> Item, whether ye know any ſpiritual Iudge
or his officers, that neglect truely with ſinceritie to myniſter Iuſtice,
according to the lawes eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, indifferently to euery party.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="02"/> Item, whether they be diligent, and vigilant
to enquire of ſuch as be noted and commonly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; ſuſpected of any
notorius crime, as of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, fornication, backbiting, dronkenneſſe,
&amp; ſuch like, and whether they be carefull to correcte ſuch offenders,
and circumſpect with charitie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme <pb facs="tcp:13673:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſmaller
faultes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> Item, whether they vſe to permitte for
ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of money the penaunce of ſuche as are notorious offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, not
caring for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil example, &amp; encorage<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of others, to commit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyke
offences, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſuffer the ſinners to ſleepe in theyr
ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> Item, whether you know any Parentes,
may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, mayſtreſſe, or dames, who doe not ſee theyr children or
youth taught the <hi>Cathechiſme,</hi> or that do not ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their ſayd
childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or youth dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church to be inſtructed therin, &amp; who
they are.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> Item, whether the Regiſter booke of
Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, mariages, and buryings, be well kept, and the names entred
accordinge to the Queene hir maieſties Iniunctions.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> Item, whether there be any Inne kepers,
Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uernes, or Ale houſe kepers, that maintaine ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinkinge in them
vppon any ſonday or holiday in the time of preaching or common prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or if
there be any faires or common markets, falling on thoſe days, whether they
open or make any ſhew of their wares before Morning prayer be ended.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> Item, whether ye knowe any Blaſphemers of
the name of God, abuſers of his holy word or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, adulterers,
fornicatours, bawds, &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayners of them, any ſuſpect of Inceſt,
any dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerdes, ribaldes, or vſers of vnſomely or filthy talk, common
ſlaunderers of their neighbours, or ſowers of diſcord betwene party and
party.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13673:7"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> Item, whether ye knowe any that miniſter
any dead mens goods without authoritie, or any executours that haue not
fulfilled the teſtatours wyll. And whether your Hoſpitalls be vſed
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the foundation thereof. And whether they receue any other then
the poore.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> Item, whether ye know any ſcholemaiſter
or inſtructour of youth that teach, not being lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully lycenſed thereto,
vnder the Biſhops Seale. Or any Phiſition or ſurgeon, that practyſe
their artes, being not lawfully authoriſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> Item, whether your ſcholemaiſters or
inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of youth, be of ſounde religion, and haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Othe to
the Queenes maieſtie, and doe bring vp his ſayde youth, in the feare of
GOD, with humilitie, obedience and good maners, to reuerence and geue place to
their elders and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and doe teach them godly ſentences of the
Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> Item, whether ye know any that vſe any
ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, Inchauntments, Magika, Necromancie, Incantations, or Witchcrafte,
or that be ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> Item, whether any of your pariſh haue
mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within the degrees of <hi>Affinitie,</hi> or <hi>Conſanguinitie,</hi>
contrary to the lawes, and a ceetayne Table for that purpoſe, laſte ſet
foorth by the moſte Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father, <hi>Mathevv,</hi> Archbyſhop of
<hi>Canterburye,</hi> or whether there be any that hath two wiues, or woman
that hath two Huſbandes, any maryed <pb facs="tcp:13673:7"/>where
a precontract was to an other, any deuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or otherwiſe ſeperated that
maryed againe, any that haue made priuie or ſecret contracts, or haue maryed
without aſking the banes not being thereunto lawfully lycenſed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn VValley. Aprilis. 15.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
